A Finding Aid to the Reginald Marsh Papers, 1897-1955, in the Archives of American Art AAA.marsregi
Archives of American Art
- Diaries, 1912-1954; Series 3; (box 3; 1 linear foot)
  Marsh's engagement diaries, dating from 1935 to 1954, and desk calendars, dating from 1931 to 1934, seem to have been used to keep track of and record his daily events and activities. Rather than typical diary entries, these comprise daily, weekly, and/or monthly calendars with brief notes on the events and activities of any given day, including meetings, classes, appointments, dinners, outings, and trips. In general, engagement diaries provide a sense of the range of artistic activities in which Marsh was involved, his interactions and associations with other artists, and the time he spent involved in teaching and other art-related endeavors. Of particular note, the "Little Red Book" diary from 1937 records Marsh's work on the mural for the New York Customs House; the one from 1938 records his work on drawings for the book, Sister Carrie; and the one from 1943 records his trip to Brazil as an artist correspondent, which included a broken arm and time spent in hospital.
  Diaries are arranged chronologically. Desk calendars are arranged in a file at the end of the series.
  - Diaries (Box 3)
    - 1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1913 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1916 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1929 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1931 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1933 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "The Little Red Book" Engagement Diaries, 1935-1939, 1943-1944, 1948-1950; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Desk Calendars, 1931-1934; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
- Notebooks, 1919-1954; Series 4; (box 4; 0.8 linear feet)
  Series consists of Marsh's notebooks, including one in which he gathered notes from a Yale course on pictorial art; ones in which he took notes on his art work and on painting techniques and media; ones which he used primarily as address books, but also to record some notes on his travels and art work; and ones in which he recorded financial information. Notebooks document Marsh's study and application of new media and techniques in his art, his work on particular art works and projects, the disposition or publication of certain works, his expenses and earnings from art, and his earnings from stocks and other sources.
  Of particular interest are Marsh's art notebooks dating from circa 1920 to 1954. Two notebooks relate to particular mural projects, a fresco project in 1935 (most likely the murals he did for the Post Office Department) and his mural project for the New York Customs House. Others consist of notes on media and painting techniques, including some notes on casein, tempera, and fresco from lectures given by Abels at the Art Students League in 1935; and notes on art work (similar to the art work diaries in Series 3), detailing time worked, what was done at different stages, and what prints were made for certain works dating from 1935 to 1944. Art notebooks also consist of lists of works (etchings, paintings, and lithographs), which typically include information about the date, dimensions, price, and/or consignment of work; notes on art expenses and contact information for models that he used; and clippings of illustrations by Marsh that were published in various magazines and newspapers during the period from circa 1920 to 1922.
  More general notebooks date from 1925 to circa 1935. These were primarily used by Marsh as address books, recording the names and numbers of friends, colleagues, and acquaintances; he also used them to record some notes on his travels, illustrations and art work, observations, and expenses. Notebooks document in particular his trip to Europe in 1925-1926, some of his ideas for New Yorker cartoons and illustrations, and his work on certain art works during the period from 1928 to 1929.
  Financial notebooks date from 1929 to 1954, and consist of Marsh's detailed notes on stock transactions, including purchases, sales, gains, and losses, and art earnings, including income from sales, royalties, teaching, and prizes. Included, to lesser extent, are notes on art expenses; interest paid on debts to Marsh by his brother, James R. Marsh; sales of art work to William Benton; bank account balances; contributions and gifts; and money borrowed. Financial notebooks document in general how Marsh made a living and supported himself as a working artist.
  Notebooks were assigned numbers at some point, though it is not clear what particular order the numbers follow nor who assigned them. The numbers appear in brackets in the respective file title. The one designated "Notebooks #9" can be found amongst the business and financial papers. Notebooks are arranged chronologically according to type. For preservation purposes, notebook pages have been removed from the leather binders in which they resided.
  - Student Notebook [#17], 1919-1920; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Student Notebook, 1919-1920; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Art Notebook [#13], Lecture Notes and Clippings of Illustrations, circa 1920-1922, 1935; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Art Notebook [#10], 1930-1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Art Notebook [#7], "Etchings and Paintings" (Lists of Work), 1930-1941 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Art Notebook [#8], Lists of Work (by type), 1930-1953 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Art Notebook [#5], Loose Notes on Media, 1930-1933, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Art Notebook [#4], Models and Expenses, 1934-1954; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Art Notebook [#6], Notes on Art Work (listed by title), 1935-1944 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Art Notebook [#2], Fresco (Post Office Mural?), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Art Notebook [#18], Custom House Murals, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Art Notebook [#11], 1938-1954; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Notebook [#15], Address Book and Notes, 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Notebook [#3], Address Book and Notes on Art Work, 1928-1929 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Notebook [#1], Address Book and Notes, 1928-1929, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Notebook [#16], Address Book and Notes on Etching, circa 1935 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Financial Notebook [#12], Stocks and Art Earnings, 1929-1954; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
  - Financial Notebook [#14], 1929-1954; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
- Sketches, 1901-1954, undated; Series 5; (boxes 4-5, OV 12-21; 1.4 linear feet)
  Series consists of Marsh's loose sketches and sketchbooks. (The bulk of Marsh's sketchbooks are held by the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York Public Library, and the Whitney Museum of American Art. These are available to view on AAA microfilm reels NRM3-NRM17.)
  In his sketches, Marsh typically recorded his environment, including the sights, scenes, and people he encountered on the city streets and the subway, in the dance and burlesque halls, and at Coney Island, as well as some of his own experiences, including his various trips to Europe (one in 1925-1926 and another in 1949). The subjects that he sketched are generally reflective of those featured in his finished art work. In his sketches, Marsh also explored ideas and created studies for paintings, and certain sketches served as the basis for finished works of art. Sketches document some of the various sources for Marsh's paintings, many of the themes that recur in his paintings and illustrations, and aspects of his creative process.
  Arrangement note
  The Sketches series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  5.1: Loose Sketches, 1921-1954, undated
  5.2: Sketchbooks, 1901-1954, undated
  - Loose Sketches, 1921-1954, undated; 5.1
    Subseries consists of sketches, as well as some preparatory drawings and studies, in pencil, ink, and occasionally watercolor. They are mostly undated, although occasionally a date appears on one or more in a file. When provided, dates or date ranges of files are meant to be suggestive of the timeframe in which the sketches were likely created.
    Individual sketches and drawings were numbered and arranged into files mostly by subject, sometimes by type or title of work, presumably by Whitney Museum staff. Files are arranged alphabetically.
    - Airplanes, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Anatomy Drawings, circa 1935-1945; (See also OV 20) (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Artists at Work, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - At the Opera, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Beach Scenes, circa 1941 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Bridge Architecture, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Bums, 1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Burlesque House, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Caricatures, undated; (See also OV 12) (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - City Sights, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Clubland, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Coney Island, undated; (See OV 13) (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Crowds in the Street, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Dali's Dream of Venus, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Dance Marathoners, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Dockside, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Electrical Execution, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Europe (Box 5)
      - Tourist Sights, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Drawings of Art Work, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Night Life, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Local Color, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 1926; (See OV 14) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Hudson Bay Fur Company, circa 1932 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Landscapes, 1922, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lifeclass Drawings, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Men Working, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Merry-Go-Rounds, circa 1944 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1921, circa 1947-1953; (See also OV 15) (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Includes some watercolors and drawings that may be by others.
    - Musicians, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Naked Over New York, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - New York, Miscellaneous, undated; (See OV 16) (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - New York Skyline, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Pick-a-Back, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Portraits, Unidentified, 1926-1927, 1954; (See also OV 17 and 19) (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Portraits, Identified, 1926; (See also OV 17) (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Prometheus at Rockefeller Center, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Scenes in Parks, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Seated Figures, undated; (See also OV 20) (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Seventeenth-century Dress, undated; (See also OV 20) (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Sideshow, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Steeplechase Park, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Subway Passengers, 1932-1953 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Subway Stations, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - [Ten Cents a Dance], circa 1933; (See OV 19) (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Theater Marquees, circa 1944 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Traffic Signals, 1949-1954 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Trains, 1931; (See also OV 20) (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Tugboats and Ships, undated; (See also OV 18) (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Under the El Tracks, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Visits to Movie and Televisions Studios, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Women (Box 5)
      - Seated Women, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Single Women in the Street, circa 1940-1951 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Groups of Women in the Street, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - Women in Front of Shops, 1939-1940s (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Women, No Setting, circa 1944-1948 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - Single Women, No Setting, 1940s-1954 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Drum Majorettes, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Modern 1939 Venus, circa 1939 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Nudes, circa 1949-1954 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Erotic Drawings, circa 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Burlesk (sic) Dancers, undated; (See also OV 19) (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - Miscellaneous, undated; (See OV 21) (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Oversize, Caricatures, undated; (See Box 4, F35) (Box OV 12)
    - Oversize, Coney Island, undated; (See Box 4, F38) (Box OV 13)
    - Oversize, Europe, Miscellaneous, 1926; (See Box 5, F5) (Box OV 14)
    - Oversize, Miscellaneous, undated; (See Box 5, F10) (Box OV 15)
    - Oversize, New York, Miscellaneous, undated; (See Box 5, F13) (Box OV 16)
    - Oversize, Portraits, Unidentified, undated; (See Box 5, F16) (Box OV 17)
    - Oversize, Portraits, Identified, 1926; (See Box 5, F17) (Box OV 17)
    - Oversize, Tugboats and Ships, undated; (See Box5, F30) (Box OV 18)
    - Oversize, Various Matted Drawings (Box OV 19)
      - Portrait, Unidentified, undated; (See Box 5, F16) (Box OV 19)
      - [Ten Cents a Dance], circa 1933; (See Box 5, F26) (Box OV 19)
      - [Burlesk Dancer?], undated; (See Box 5, F43) (Box OV 19)
    - Oversize, Various Sketches (Box OV 20)
      - Anatomy Drawing, undated; (See Box 4, F28) (Box OV 20)
      - Seated Figures, undated; (See Box 5, F19) (Box OV 20)
      - Seventeenth-century Dress, undated; (See Box 5, F20) (Box OV 20)
      - Trains, undated; (See Box 5, F29) (Box OV 20)
    - Oversize, Women, Miscellaneous, undated; (See Box 5, F44) (Box OV 21)
  - Sketchbooks, 1901-1954, and undated; 5.2
    Subseries consists of several sketchbooks, including ones comprised of portraits, studies, and rough sketches of various subjects, as well as one of childhood art work dating from 1900, one documenting his trip to Europe in 1949, and one of erotic drawings.
    Sketchbooks were assigned numbers at some point, though it is not clear what particular order the numbers follow nor who assigned them. The numbers appear in brackets in the respective file title. Sketchbooks are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Sketchbook [#26], Childhood Art Work, 1901-1918, 1938; (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 46-47)
    - Sketchbook, Portraits and City Scenes, circa 1920s? (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Sketchbook [#36], Various Subjects, circa 1940s-1954 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Sketchbook [#27], Studies and Anatomy Drawings, 1942-1947 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Sketchbook [#28], Various Subjects, 1942-1945 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Sketchbook [#22], Various Subjects, 1948-1954; (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 52-55)
    - Sketches in Sample Book of Tracing and Drawing Paper, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Sketchbook [#43], Europe, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Sketchbook, Erotic Drawings, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Sketchbook Fragment, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Scrapbooks, 1911-1954; Series 6; (boxes 6, 9-11; 1.5 linear feet)
  Series consists of the scrapbooks that Marsh kept throughout his career as an artist, in which he saved clippings of reproductions of his work (illustrations, cartoons, and reproductions of paintings and theater designs), articles, and reviews that appeared in various newspapers and magazines along with other printed material. Scrapbooks document the trajectory of Marsh's career, including the publication of his illustrations and cartoons, the exhibition of his paintings, and the critical and public reception of his art work. Notably, scrapbooks also document Marsh's on-going effort to record and recount his whole career in the clippings he collected and in the way he sometimes creatively displayed them.
  Scrapbooks were assigned numbers at some point, though it is not clear what particular order the numbers follow nor who assigned them. The numbers appear in brackets in the respective file title. At some previous point, scrapbooks that had been stored in 3-ring binders were removed from them for preservation purposes. Scrapbbooks are arranged in rough chronological order. More detailed descriptions of certain ones are provided below.
  - Scrapbook [#11], Reproductions of Work in The Nutley Bulletin and Other Juvenilia, 1911-1915, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook [#10], Reproductions of Work in The Yale Record, 1916-1917; (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Scrapbook [#2], Reproductions of Work in The Yale Record, 1917-1920 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook [#3], Clippings, 1920-circa 1928; (See Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Clippings include Marsh's illustrations for various newspapers and magazines, vaudeville reviews for The Daily News (from 1923 to 1925), articles on Marsh, and reproductions of various works. Also included are some watercolor sketches.
  - Scrapbook [#1], Clippings, circa 1922-1939 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Clippings include articles on Marsh and his art work, reviews of his exhibitions (including shows at the Whitney Studio, Weyhe Gallery, and Rehn Galleries, as well as in the department store, Wanamaker's), and reproductions of his paintings.
  - Scrapbook [#4], Clippings, 1925-1944 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Clippings are assembled in a more creative fashion and include articles about Marsh, reviews of exhibitions, some vaudeville reviews, reproductions of paintings (including the Custom House murals), and illustrations for The New Yorker.
  - Scrapbook [#6], Photographs and Clippings, circa 1927-1930; (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
    Included are photographs of some early works, including a portrait of Marsh by Katherine Schmidt, several self-portraits, paintings of locomotives, and some theater designs. Clippings include illustrations and cartoons for The New Yorker.
  - Scrapbook [#5], Clippings of Illustrations, circa 1929-1945; (See Box 10) (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Included are clippings of Marsh's illustrations for The New Yorker and, to a lesser extent, for other magazines such as Vanity Fair, Harper's Bazaar and Vogue. Also included are some of Marsh's book illustrations.
  - Scrapbook [#7], Clippings, Letters, and Exhibition Catalogs, 1930-1945; (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
    Clippings include articles on Marsh and his art work, reviews of his exhibitions, and his illustrations. Also included are letters relating to the gift or purchase of Marsh's art work (including letters from Philadelphia Museum and Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts) and to prizes awarded to Marsh for his art work (including a letter from the director of the Corcoran Gallery of Art about the gold medal being awarded to his painting, "Strip Tease in New Jersey," and a letter from the Art Institute of Chicago regarding the prize awarded to "Summer in New York"). Also found are exhibition catalogs for several of Marsh's shows (especially at the Rehn Galleries) and for Isabel Bishop's shows.
  - Scrapbook [#8], Clippings, 1931-1945; (See Box 10) (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Clippings include articles about Marsh and his art work, including ones on the Custom House murals and his use of egg tempera, in magazines such as Esquire and American Artist; his illustrations for magazines such Vogue, Life, and Fortune; and an article by Marsh entitled "Let's Get Back to Painting." Also included are printed greeting cards featuring Marsh's art work and some book cover illustrations.
  - Scrapbook, Clipping of Article on Marsh, "Reginald Marsh as a Painter,", 1933 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook [#9], Clippings, Awards, and Other Material, 1943-1954; (See Box 11) (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Clippings include articles on Marsh, reproductions of his work, some reviews of his exhibitions, and his illustrations. Awards include the Gold Medal in Graphic Arts from and a certificate of election to the National Institute of Arts and Letters, and a certificate from National Academy of Design. Also included are book covers designed by Marsh, exhibition catalogs, and a printed greeting card.
  - Scrapbook, Clipping of Article by Marsh, "Let's Get Back to Painting," and Other Clippings, 1944-1947; (See Box 11) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Oversize, Scrapbook [#3], Clippings, 1920-circa 1928; (See Box 6, F6) (Box 9 (sol))
  - Oversize, Scrapbook [#5], Clippings of Illustrations, circa 1929-1945; (See Box 6, F12) (Box 10 (sol))
  - Oversize, Scrapbook [#8], Clippings, 1931-1945; (See Box 6, F17) (Box 10 (sol))
  - Oversize, Scrapbook [#9], Clippings, Awards, and Other Material, 1943-1954; (See Box 6, F19) (Box 11 (sol))
  - Oversize, Scrapbook, Clippings of Article by Marsh, "Let's Get Back to Painting," and Other Clippings, 1944-1947; (See Box 6, F20) (Box 11 (sol))
- Business and Financial Papers, 1923-1954; Series 7; (box 6; 0.3 linear feet)
  Series consists of scattered material relating to various business matters, practical concerns, and financial aspects involved in carrying out Marsh's artistic projects, such as contracts and agreements, royalty statements from the sales of greeting cards, receipts for works on consignment, receipts and notes relating to his work on the murals for the Treasury Department. Also included is some paperwork relating to his assignment as an artist correspondent in Brazil and travel arrangements for various trips. Business and financial papers are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Contracts and Agreements, 1923-1937 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Permissions and Authorizations, 1925, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Royalty Statements, Consignment Receipts, and Other Material, 1928-1954 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Rehn Galleries Statements, 1929-1954 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Gallery Statements, Receipts, and Correspondence, 1930-1952 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Receipts and Notes Relating to Treasury Department Art Project Murals, circa 1937 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938-1953 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Paperwork Relating to Assignment in Brazil, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Paperwork Relating to General Travel, 1949-1953 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Lists, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Business Cards, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Photographs, circa 1897-1908, 1920-1952; Series 8; (boxes 6-8, 10; 1.3 linear feet)
  Series consists of photographs of Marsh's family, the artist at work, and his art work, as well as some unidentified (presumably personal) photographs and some photographs of art work by others.
  The Photographs series is organized 3 subseries:
  8.1: Family and Personal, circa 1897-1908, circa 1920, undated
  8.2: Artist, undated
  8.3: Art Work, 1920s-1952
  - Family and Personal, circa 1897-1908, circa 1920, undated; 8.1
    Subseries consists of photographs of Marsh's family, some of which are loose and some of which are on pages from a photograph album. Though the individuals in the photographs are typically not identified by name, it is possible to identify Marsh's parents, siblings and Marsh himself as a child amongst some of the photographs. Also included are a picture postcard of Marsh as a young man with some friends; photographs of friends, Augustus Kelly and Llewelyn Powys; and various unidentified photographs presumably collected by Marsh. Photographs are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Marsh Family Photographs, circa 1897-1908, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Loose Photographs from Family Photo Album, circa 1897-1905, undated; (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 33-34)
    - Pages from Family Photo Album, undated; (See Box 10) (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Picture Postcard of Marsh and Friends, circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Photographs of Friends, 1937, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Photographs of Marsh's Father, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Oversize, Pages from Family Photo Album, undated; (See Box 6, F34) (Box 10 (sol))
  - Artist, undated; 8.2
    Subseries consists of photographs of Marsh at work as an artist. Photographs taken by Gene Pyle show Marsh observing and sketching the crowds and scenes in and around what is most likely Coney Island. Other photographs (photographer unknown) show Marsh sketching people on the streets of New York and painting in his studio.
    - Photographs of Marsh Sketching (taken by Gene Pyle), undated; (See Box 10) (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Contact Sheets of Photographs of Marsh Sketching (taken by Gene Pyle), undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs of Marsh Sketching and Painting, undated (Box 6, Folder 42)